<styleguide revision="BJCP_2015" language="en">
    <category id="C">
        <revision number="1">BJCP_2015</revision>
        <name>Cider 2015</name>
        <subcategory id="CI">
            <name>Introduction to Cider Guidelines</name>
            <notes title="">The following discussion applies to all the cider styles, except where explicitly
                superseded in the sub-category guidelines. This introduction identifies common characteristics and
                descriptions for all types of cider, and should be used as a reference whenever entering or judging
                cider.
            </notes>
            <notes title="">
                <strong>Cider</strong>
                is fermented apple juice.
                <strong>Perry</strong>
                is fermented pear juice. There are two categories for cider and perry:
                <i>Standard Cider and Perry</i>
                (Category C1) and
                <i>Specialty Cider and Perry</i>
                (Category C2). The Standard category covers ciders and perries made primarily or entirely from the
                juice of apples or pears (but not both at once). The only adjunct permitted in the Standard
                category, and only in some sub-categories, is a limited addition of sugar to achieve a suitable
                starting gravity or to raise sweetness post-fermentation. Note that honey is not a &#8220;sugar&#8221;
                for this purpose; a cider made with added honey must be entered either as a Specialty cider or as a
                Cyser under the appropriate mead sub-category. Other sugar sources that also add significant flavors
                (brown sugar, molasses) would also create a Specialty cider (such as New England style).
            </notes>
            <notes title="Aroma and Flavor">
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        Ciders and perries do not necessarily present overtly fruity aromas or flavors &#8212; in
                        the same sense that a wine does not taste overtly of grapes. Drier styles of cider in
                        particular develop more complex but less fruity characters. A simple
                        <i>apple soda</i>
                        or
                        <i>wine cooler</i>
                        character is not desirable in a cider or perry.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Some styles of cider exhibit distinctly
                        <strong>non-</strong>
                        fruity tastes or aromas, such as the
                        <i>smoky ham</i>
                        undertones of a dry English cider.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The
                        <strong>sweetness</strong>
                        (residual sugar, or RS) of a cider or perry may vary from absolutely dry (no RS) to as much
                        as a sweet dessert wine (10% or more RS). In sweeter ciders, other components of taste
                        &#8212; particularly acidity &#8212; must balance the sweetness. The level of sweetness must
                        be specified so organizers and judges can arrange flights of tastings and entries within
                        flights. Tasting should always proceed from drier to sweeter. There are five categories of
                        sweetness, expanded from three in earlier guidelines. Note that the numbers for these levels
                        are
                        <strong>not</strong>
                        rigid or restrictive. They are intended to guide the cidermaker on how to enter, not to be
                        used as judging criteria unless a cider is declared at a sweetness level far from its actual
                        sweetness. Judges must realize that sweetness can mask faults. Be more attentive to this in
                        a sweeter cider. Likewise, do not penalize dry ciders excessively for minor faults which may
                        be more evident only because of lack of sweetness. The categories and
                        <i>approximate</i>
                        sugar levels are as follows. Final gravities are particularly rough numbers since they
                        cannot take account of what the SG would be if the cider fermented out completely.
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                <strong>Dry:</strong>
                                below 0.4% residual sugar. This corresponds to a final specific gravity less than
                                1.002. There is no perception of sweetness.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <strong>Medium-dry:</strong>
                                0.4-0.9% residual sugar. This corresponds to a final specific gravity of
                                1.002-1.004. There is a hint of sweetness but the cider is still perceived primarily
                                as dry. Also known as semi-dry.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <strong>Medium:</strong>
                                in the range between dry and sweet, 0.9-2.0% residual sugar, final gravity
                                1.004-1.009. Sweetness is now a notable component of the overall character.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <strong>Medium-sweet:</strong>
                                2.0-4.0% residual sugar, final gravity 1.009-1.019. The cider is sweet but still
                                refreshing. Also known as semi-sweet.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <strong>Sweet:</strong>
                                above 4.0% residual sugar, roughly equivalent to a final gravity of over 1.019. The
                                cider has the character of a dessert wine. It must not be cloying; see notes on
                                balance.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>If a cider is close to one of these boundaries, it should be identified by the sweetness
                        category which best describes the overall impression it gives. The five categories above
                        were expanded from the earlier three dry-medium-sweet by splitting the dry and medium
                        categories.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <strong>Acidity</strong>
                        is an essential element of cider and perry: it must be sufficient to give a clean,
                        refreshing impression without being puckering. Acidity (from malic and in some cases lactic
                        acids) must not be confused with acetification (from ethyl acetate or acetic acid&#8212;vinegar).
                        The acrid aroma and tingling taste of acetification is a fault.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Ciders and perries vary considerably in
                        <strong>tannin</strong>
                        . This affects both bitterness and astringency (see
                        <i>Mouthfeel</i>
                        below). If made from culinary or table fruit, tannins are typically low; nevertheless some
                        tannin is desirable to balance the character. The character contributed by tannin should be
                        mainly astringency rather than bitterness. An overt or forward bitterness is a fault, and is
                        often due to processing techniques rather than fruit character.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Cider may go through a
                        <strong>malo-lactic fermentation</strong>
                        (MLF) which converts some or all of the sharp malic acid to softer, less-acidic lactic acid.
                        (Perries should not go through MLF because it will cause undesirable acetification.) In
                        ciders made with tannic apples, the MLF commonly produces ethylphenols which are evident as
                        other flavors: spicy/smoky including smoked meat, phenolic, and farmyard/old-horse. These
                        flavors are desirable although not mandatory in English and French styles, but must not be
                        <i>over the top</i>. The spicy-smoky character is the most desirable of the three. Note that
                        a dominating farmyard character may be the result of a Brettanomyces contamination rather
                        than MLF; this is a serious fault. Also, because MLF reduces the acidity of a cider, the
                        result should not be
                        <i>flabby</i>
                        or too soft; the cider must remain refreshing. Finally, judges should be attentive to the
                        possibility of faults such as mousiness which are more likely in a higher pH cider that has
                        gone through MLF. (Some judges may be unable to detect
                        <i>mouse</i>; an alkaline oral rinse may be needed to confirm and reach agreement among
                        judges.)
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </notes>
            <notes title="Appearance">
                <ul>
                    <li>Clarity may vary from good to brilliant. The lack of sparkling clarity is not a fault, but
                        visible particles are undesirable. In some styles a &#8220;rustic&#8221; lack of brilliance
                        is common. Perries are notoriously difficult to clear; as a result a slight haze is not a
                        fault. However, a &#8220;sheen&#8221; in either cider or perry generally indicates the early
                        stage of lactic contamination and is a distinct fault.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Carbonation may vary from entirely still to a champagne level. No or little carbonation is
                        termed
                        <strong>still</strong>
                        . A still cider may give a slight
                        <i>tickle on the tongue</i>. A moderate carbonation level is termed
                        <strong>petillant</strong>
                        . Highly carbonated is termed
                        <strong>sparkling</strong>
                        . At the higher levels of carbonation, the
                        <i>mousse</i>
                        (head) may be retained for a short time. However, gushing, foaming, and difficult-to-manage
                        heads are faults.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </notes>
            <notes title="Mouthfeel">
                <ul>
                    <li>In general, cider and perry have a body and fullness akin to a light wine. The body is much
                        less than that of beer. Mouthfeel depends on tannin level. Tannic styles (English and
                        French) will have astringent mouthfeel resembling a red wine. Full-sparkling ciders will be
                        champagne-like.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </notes>
            <notes title="Ingredients">
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        The apple and pear varieties are intended to illustrate commonly used examples, not dictate
                        requirements when making the style. In general, adjuncts and additives are prohibited except
                        where specifically allowed in particular styles, and then the entrant must state them.
                        Common processing aids, and enzymes, are generally allowed as long as they are not
                        detectable in the finished cider. Yeast used for cider/perry may be either
                        <i>natural</i>
                        (the yeast which occurs on the fruit itself and/or is retained in the milling and pressing
                        equipment) or
                        <i>cultured</i>
                        yeast. Malo-lactic fermentation is allowed, either naturally occurring or with an added ML
                        culture. Enzymes may be used for clarification of the juice prior to fermentation. Malic
                        acid may be added to a low-acid juice to bring acidity up to a level considered safe for
                        avoiding bacterial contamination and off-flavors (typically pH 3.8 or below). Sulfites may
                        be added as needed for microbiological control. If used, the maximum accepted safe level for
                        sulfites (200 mg/l) must be strictly observed; moreover, any excess sulfite that is
                        detectable in the finished cider (a &#8220;burning match&#8221; character) is a serious
                        fault.
                    </li>
                    <li>If a cider is to have sweetness (residual sugar), this may be obtained by arresting
                        fermentation or back-sweetening with sugar or fresh juice. In this case, entrant must ensure
                        that the cider is stable. Turbidity, gushing, or foaming resulting from restarted
                        fermentation in-bottle are considered serious faults.
                    </li>
                    <li>If the cider is fermented and/or aged with wood (barrel, chips, staves/strips), the type of
                        wood and process must be declared. Except for category C2F (Specialty Cider/Perry), the wood
                        character must be no more than barely recognizable. A cider with substantial wood/barrel
                        character entered in any category other than C2F will be regarded as not in the style.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Sorbate may be added at bottling to stabilize the cider. However, any residual aroma/flavor
                        from excessive use or misuse of sorbate (e.g., a
                        <i>geranium</i>
                        note) is a distinct fault.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        Carbonation may be either natural (by maintaining CO
                        <sub>2</sub>pressure through processing or by bottle-conditioning) or added (by CO
                        <sub>2</sub>injection). In most categories, a still (completely uncarbonated) cider is
                        appropriate. Judges must realize that carbonation can improve a naive impression of a cider
                        and must not penalize still ciders (when declared properly) for lack of carbonation.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </notes>
        </subcategory>
        <category id="C1">
            <name>Standard Cider and Perry</name>
            <notes>The styles represented in this category are the principal established styles. "New World" is simply a
                name change from the "Common" of earlier versions.
            </notes>
            <notes>There are known styles not represented here. In particular, Spanish (Asturian and Basque) does not
                yet have a style definition because there is presently insufficient appreciation and understanding, as
                well as a lack of commercial examples of known quality for reference.
            </notes>
            <notes>In the case of a cider made to a style not explicitly represented here, it should be entered in the
                closest applicable category. The first decision is whether the cider was made with apples with
                significant tannin content that gives the cider noticeable astringency or bitterness. If not, it should
                be entered as a New World Cider. If so, the choice is between the English and French sub-categories;
                this decision should be based on whether the cider tends more toward sweet, rich, somewhat fruity
                (French) or drier and more austere (English). For perry of a non-represented style, the decision is, as
                above, based on tannin content. If in doubt, enter as New World Perry.
            </notes>
            <subcategory id="C1A">
                <name>New World Cider</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    A
                    <strong>New World Cider</strong>
                    is made from culinary/table apples, with wild or crab apples often used for acidity/tannin balance.
                    Compared to other styles in this category, these ciders are generally relatively lower in tannin and
                    higher in acidity. "New World" references the style, not a location, as ciders in this style are
                    also made in eastern England, Australia, Germany, etc.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>A refreshing drink of some substance - not bland or watery. Sweet ciders must not be
                    cloying. Dry ciders must not be too austere.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Sweet or low-alcohol ciders may have apple aroma and flavor. Dry ciders will be more wine-like
                    with some esters. Sugar and acidity should combine to give a refreshing character. Acidity is medium
                    to high, refreshing, but must not be harsh or biting.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Clear to brilliant, pale to medium gold in color.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Medium body. Some tannin should be present for slight to moderate astringency, but little
                    bitterness.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Comments</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>An ideal cider serves well as a "session" drink, and suitably accompanies a wide variety of
                    food.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 categories). If OG is substantially above typical range, entrant should
                    explain, e.g., particular variety of apple giving high-gravity juice.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Varieties</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Common (Winesap, Macintosh, Golden Delicious, Braeburn, Jonathan), multi-use (Northern
                    Spy,
                    Russets, Baldwin), crabapples, any suitable wildings.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] Uncle John's Fruit House Winery Apple Hard Cider, Tandem Ciders Pretty Penny (MI),
                    Bellwether Spyglass (NY), West County Pippin (MA), White Winter Hard Apple Cider (WI), Wandering
                    Aengus Ciderworks Bloom (OR), &#198;ppeltreow Appely Brut and Doux (WI).
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.045</low>
                    <high>1.065</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>0.995</low>
                    <high>1.020</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>5</low>
                    <high>8</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C1B">
                <name>English Cider</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    <strong>English Cider</strong>
                    includes the English "West Country" plus ciders inspired by that style. These ciders are made with
                    bittersweet and bitter-sharp apple varieties cultivated specifically for cider making. English
                    ciders are traditionally fermented and aged in wood barrels, which adds some character; however, the
                    barrels used are rarely new, so there is no overt wood character.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Generally dry, full-bodied, austere. Complex flavor profile, long finish.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    No overt apple character, but various flavors and esters that suggest apples, particularly tannic
                    varieties. English-style ciders commonly go through MLF (see
                    <i>Introduction/Aroma-and-Flavor</i>) which produces desirable spicy/smoky, phenolic, and
                    farmyard/old-horse characters. These flavor notes are positive but
                    <strong>not</strong>
                    required. If present, they must not dominate; in particular, the phenolic and farmyard notes should
                    not be heavy. A strong farmyard character without spicy/smoky or phenolic suggests a
                    <i>Brettanomyces</i>
                    contamination, which is a fault. Mousiness is a serious fault.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Barely cloudy to brilliant. Medium yellow to amber color.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Full. Moderate to high tannin, perceived as astringency and some bitterness. Carbonation
                    still to moderate. Bottle-fermented or -conditioned ciders may have high carbonation, up to
                    champagne levels, but not gushing or foaming.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Comments</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Sweet examples exist, but dry is most traditional, particularly when considering the drying
                    contributions of tannin.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (dry through medium-sweet, 4 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MAY</strong>
                    specify variety of apple for a single varietal cider; if specified, varietal character will be
                    expected.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Varieties</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Kingston Black, Stoke Red, Dabinett, Porter's Perfection, Nehou, Yarlington Mill, Major,
                    various Jerseys, etc.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] Westcott Bay Traditional Very Dry, Dry and Medium Sweet (WA), Farnum Hill Extra-Dry, Dry,
                    and Farmhouse (NH), Wandering Aengus Oaked Dry (OR), Montana CiderWorks North Fork (MT), Bellwether
                    Heritage (NY). [UK] Oliver's Traditional Dry, Hogan's Dry and Medium Dry, Henney's Dry and Vintage
                    Still, Burrow Hill Medium, Aspall English Imperial.
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.050</low>
                    <high>1.075</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>0.995</low>
                    <high>1.015</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>6</low>
                    <high>9</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C1C">
                <name>French Cider</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    <strong>French Cider</strong>
                    includes Normandy styles plus ciders inspired by those styles, including ciders made by various
                    techniques to achieve the French flavor profile. These ciders are made with bittersweet and
                    bitter-sharp apple varieties cultivated specifically for cider making.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    Traditional French procedures use small amounts of salt and calcium compounds (calcium chloride,
                    calcium carbonate) to aid the process of pectin coagulation. These compounds may be used,
                    pre-fermentation, but in limited quantity. It is a fault if judges can detect a salty or chalky
                    taste. The enzyme PME (pectin methyl esterase) may also be used pre-fermentation for pectin
                    coagulation.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Note that the sweetness/gravity levels indicate an overall tendency, not a sharp delineation
                    between English and French ciders.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Medium to sweet, full-bodied, rich.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Fruity character/aroma. This may come from slow or arrested fermentation (in the French technique of
                    <i>d&#233;f&#233;cation</i>) or approximated by back-sweetening with juice. Tends to a rich
                    fullness. MLF notes of spicy-smoky, phenolic, and farmyard are common but not required (just as with
                    English style), and must not be pronounced. The French expect more subtle MLF character than do the
                    English.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Clear to brilliant, medium yellow to amber color.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Medium to full, mouth-filling. Moderate tannin, perceived mainly as astringency. Carbonation
                    moderate to champagne-like, but at higher levels it must not gush or foam.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Comments</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Typically made sweet to balance the tannin levels from the traditional apple varieties.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (medium to sweet only, 3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MAY</strong>
                    specify variety of apple for a single varietal cider; if specified, varietal character will be
                    expected.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Varieties</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Nehou, Muscadet de Dieppe, Reine des Pommes, Michelin, etc.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] West County Reine de Pomme (MA), [France] Eric Bordelet (various), Etienne Dupont,
                    Etienne Dupont Organic, Bellot
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.050</low>
                    <high>1.065</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.010</low>
                    <high>1.020</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>3</low>
                    <high>6</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C1D">
                <name>New World Perry</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    <strong>New World Perry</strong>
                    is made from culinary/table pears.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Mild. Medium to medium-sweet. Still to lightly sparkling. Only very slight acetification is
                    acceptable. Mousiness, ropy/oily characters are serious faults.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>There is a pear character, but not obviously fruity. It tends toward that of a young white
                    wine.
                    No bitterness.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Slightly cloudy to clear. Generally quite pale.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Relatively full, low to moderate tannin apparent as astringency.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Comments</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Some table pears may contain significant amounts of sorbitol, in which case a
                    <i>dry</i>
                    perry may give an impression of sweetness due to sorbitol in the pears. Perception of sorbitol as
                    <i>sweet</i>
                    is highly variable from one person to the next. Hence, entrants should specify sweetness according
                    to actual residual sugar amount, and judges must be aware that they might perceive more sweetness
                    than how the perry was entered.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 categories).
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Varieties</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Bartlett, Kiefer, Comice, Conference, etc.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] White Winter Paarynat (WI), Uncle John's Fruit House Winery Perry (MI)
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.050</low>
                    <high>1.060</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.000</low>
                    <high>1.020</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>5</low>
                    <high>7</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C1E">
                <name>Traditional Perry</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Traditional perry is made from pears grown specifically for that purpose rather than for eating
                    or cooking. Many "perry pears" are nearly inedible due to high tannins; some are also quite hard.
                    Perry pears may contain substantial amounts of sorbitol, a non-fermentable sweet-tasting compound.
                    Hence a perry can be completely dry (no residual sugar) yet taste sweet.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Tannic. Medium to medium-sweet. Still to lightly sparkling. Only very slight acetification
                    is acceptable. Mousiness and ropy/oily characters are serious faults.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>There is a pear character, but not obviously fruity. It tends toward that of a young white
                    wine.
                    Some slight bitterness.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Slightly cloudy to clear. Generally quite pale.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Relatively full, moderate to high tannin apparent as astringency.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Comments</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Note that a
                    <i>dry</i>
                    perry may give an impression of sweetness due to sorbitol in the pears, and perception of sorbitol
                    as
                    <i>sweet</i>
                    is highly variable from one person to the next. Hence entrants should specify sweetness according to
                    actual residual sugar amount, and judges must be aware that they might perceive more sweetness than
                    how the perry was entered.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 categories). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    <strong/>state variety of pear(s) used.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Varieties</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Butt, Gin, Brandy, Barland, Blakeney Red, Thorn, Moorcroft, etc.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] &#198;ppeltreow Orchard Oriole Perry (WI); [France] Bordelet Poire Authentique and Poire
                    Granit, Christian Drouin Poire, [UK] Oliver's Classic, Blakeney Red, and Herefordshire Dry; Hogan's
                    Vintage Perry.
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.050</low>
                    <high>1.070</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.000</low>
                    <high>1.020</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>5</low>
                    <high>9</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
        </category>
        <category id="C2">
            <name>Specialty Cider and Perry</name>
            <notes>
                Specialty cider/perry includes beverages made with added flavorings (spices and/or other fruits), those
                made with substantial amounts of sugar-sources to increase starting gravities, and the beverage made
                from a combination of apple and pear juice (sometimes called
                <i>pider</i>
                ).
            </notes>
            <notes>The same general characteristics and fault descriptions apply to specialty ciders as to standard
                ciders (preceding category), with the exception of added ingredients allowed.
            </notes>
            <subcategory id="C2A">
                <name>New England Cider</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    This is a cider made with characteristic New England apples for relatively high acidity, with
                    additives to raise alcohol levels and contribute additional flavor notes.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Substantial body and character. Typically relatively dry, but can be somewhat sweet if in
                    balance and not containing hot alcohol.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>A flavorful cider with robust apple character, strong alcohol, and derivative flavors from
                    sugar
                    additives; traditionally dry.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Clear to brilliant, pale to medium yellow.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Substantial, alcoholic. Moderate tannin.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Comments</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Additives may include white and brown sugars, molasses, small amounts of honey, and raisins.
                    Additives are intended to raise OG well above that which would be achieved by apples alone. This
                    style is sometimes barrel-aged, in which case there will be oak character as with a barrel-aged
                    wine. If the barrel was formerly used to age spirits, some flavor notes from the spirit (e.g.,
                    whisky or rum) may also be present, but must be subtle.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify if the cider was barrel-fermented or aged. Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 levels).
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Varieties</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Northern Spy, Roxbury Russet, Golden Russet, Baldwin, etc.; many traditional New England
                    apples.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] Snowdrift Semi-Dry (WA), Blackbird Cider Works New England Style (NY).
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.060</low>
                    <high>1.100</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>0.995</low>
                    <high>1.020</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>7</low>
                    <high>13</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C2B">
                <name>Cider with Other Fruit</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    This is a cider with other fruits or fruit-juices added - for example, berry. This is the correct
                    style to enter a beverage fermented from a combination of apple and pear juice.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Like a white wine with complex flavors. The apple character must marry with the added fruit
                    so that neither one dominates the other.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    The cider character must be present and must fit with the other fruits. It is a fault if the added
                    fruit(s) completely dominate; a judge might ask,
                    <i>Would this be different if neutral spirits replaced the cider?</i>
                    A fruit cider should not be like an alco-pop. Oxidation is a fault.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Clear to brilliant. Color appropriate to added fruit, but should not show oxidation
                    characteristics. (For example, red berries should give red-to-purple color, not orange.)
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Substantial. May be significantly tannic, depending on fruit added.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 categories). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify all fruit(s) and/or fruit juice(s) added.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] West County Blueberry-Apple Wine (MA), Bellwether Cherry Street (NY), Uncle John's Fruit
                    Farm Winery Apple Cherry, Apple Blueberry, and Apricot Apple Hard Cider (MI)
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.045</low>
                    <high>1.070</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>0.995</low>
                    <high>1.010</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>5</low>
                    <high>9</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C2C">
                <name>Applewine</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    The term for this category is traditional but possibly misleading: it is simply a cider with
                    substantial added sugar to achieve higher alcohol than a standard cider. As such it comes closer to
                    a white wine than any other style. No fruit other than apples may be used in this style.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Typically like a dry white wine, balanced, and with low astringency and bitterness.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Comparable to a New World Cider. Cider character must be distinctive. Very dry to sweet,
                    although often dry.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Clear to brilliant, pale to medium-gold. Cloudiness or hazes are inappropriate.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Lighter than other ciders, because higher alcohol is derived from addition of sugar rather
                    than juice. Carbonation may range from still to champagne-like.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 levels).
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] Uncle John's Fruit House Winery Fruit House Apple (MI), McClure's Sweet Apple Wine
                    (IN).
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.070</low>
                    <high>1.100</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>0.995</low>
                    <high>1.020</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>9</low>
                    <high>12</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C2D">
                <name>Ice Cider</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    This is a cider style in which the juice is concentrated before fermentation either by freezing
                    fruit before pressing or freezing juice and removing water. Fermentation stops or is arrested before
                    reaching dryness. The character differs from Applewine in that the ice cider process increases not
                    only sugar (hence alcohol) but acidity and all fruit flavor components proportionately. No additives
                    are permitted in this style; in particular, sweeteners may not be used to increase gravity. This
                    style originated in Quebec in the 1990s.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Fruity, smooth, sweet-tart. Acidity must be enough to prevent it being cloying.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Brilliant. Color is deeper than a standard cider, gold to amber.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Full body. May be tannic (astringent and/or bitter) but this should be slight, to moderate at
                    most.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify starting gravity, final gravity or residual sugar, and alcohol level. Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels).
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Varieties</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Usually North American classic table fruit such as McIntosh or Cortland.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] various from Eden Ice Cider Company and Champlain Orchards. [Canada] Domaine Pinnacle,
                    Les Vergers de la Colline, and Cidrerie St-Nicolas (Quebec).
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.130</low>
                    <high>1.180</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.060</low>
                    <high>1.085</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>7</low>
                    <high>13</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C2E">
                <name>Cider with Herbs/Spices</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    This is a cider with any combination of "botanicals" added. Hopped ciders are included in this
                    category. Other examples are ciders with "apple pie" spices (cinnamon, nutmeg, allspice), ginger,
                    lemon grass, herbal tea blends, etc.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Impression</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Like a white wine with complex flavors. The apple character must marry with the botanicals
                    and give a balanced result.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    The cider character must be present and must fit with the botanicals. As with a fruit cider, it is a
                    fault if the botanicals dominate; a judge might ask,
                    <i>Would this be different if neutral spirits replaced the cider?</i>
                    Oxidation of either the base cider or the additions is a fault.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Clear to brilliant. Color appropriate to added botanicals.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Average or more. Cider may be tannic from effect of botanicals but must not be bitter from
                    over-extraction.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 categories). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify all botanicals added. If hops are used, entrant must specify variety/varieties used.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] Colorado Cider Grasshop-ah (CO), Wandering Aengus Anthem Hops (OR).
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.045</low>
                    <high>1.070</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>0.995</low>
                    <high>1.010</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>5</low>
                    <high>9</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
            <subcategory id="C2F">
                <name>Specialty Cider/Perry</name>
                <body>
                    <big>
                        <b>Notes</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    This is an open-ended category for cider or perry with other ingredients such that it does not
                    fit any of the categories above. This includes the use of other sweeteners. A cider with added honey
                    may be entered here if the cider character remains dominant; otherwise it should be entered as mead
                    in the cyser sub-category. Examples also include wood-fermented or aged ciders in which the
                    wood/barrel character is a significant part of the overall flavor profile.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Flavor</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>The cider character must always be present, and must fit with added ingredients. If a spirit
                    barrel was used, the character of the spirit (rum, whiskey, etc.) must be no more than just
                    recognizable; it must not be a substantial element of the flavor.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Appearance</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Clear to brilliant. Color should be that of a standard cider unless other ingredients are
                    expected to contribute color.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Mouthfeel</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>Average body, may show tannic (astringent) or heavy body as determined by other
                    ingredients.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Entry Instructions</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>
                    Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify all ingredients. Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify carbonation level (3 levels). Entrants
                    <strong>MUST</strong>
                    specify sweetness (5 categories).
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    <big>
                        <b>Examples</b>
                    </big>
                    <br/>[US] Finn River Fire Barrel (WA)
                </body>
                <stats>
                    <type>og</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>1.045</low>
                    <high>1.100</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>fg</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>0.995</low>
                    <high>1.020</high>
                </stats>
                <stats>
                    <type>abv</type>
                    <header></header>
                    <notes></notes>
                    <low>5</low>
                    <high>12</high>
                </stats>
            </subcategory>
        </category>
    </category>
</styleguide>